Acknowledgements

This edited volume is the culmination of efforts and insights from a diverse group of individuals, whose contributions during the article review and selection process have been invaluable. While many of these contributors, hailing from Japan and Nepal, remain unnamed, their support has not gone unnoticed.

I extend my heartfelt gratitude to Senior Lecturer M.M. Ihjas from the University of Peradeniya, Sri Lanka, whose early involvement and guidance have been instrumental to this project. A special thanks goes to my friend Hari Bahadur Khadka of Tribhuvan University, Nepal for engaging in thought-provoking academic debates on contemporary issues. Additionally, the contributions of Aishwarya K.C. and Prakhyat K.C. have been particularly noteworthy.

Above all, my deepest appreciation is reserved for my family—my mother Gaumati Karki, my sisters Sita Kumari K.C. and Rita Kumari Karki, my wife Thapa Kalpana and my children Anmol, Ashima and Aavash. Their unwavering love and support have created a nurturing environment that has been essential to my work. This book would not have been possible without the sanctuary they provide.

1 May 2024

PURNA BAHADUR KARKI

CHAPTER 1

Nepal’s Political Parties and the
Rise of Communists in
Mainstream Politics

BHIM NATH REGMI

Nepal—a South Asian country has approximately 26.5 million people occupying a horizontal strip of land between two neighbours India and China. It is an immensely diverse country and the Constitution of Nepal 2015 accepts ‘. . . Nepal is a multicultural, multilingual, multi-religious, multi-ethnic’ by all measures, including geography and caste. Prithvi Narayan Shah appeared ready for battle and determined to bring together the smaller states of Nepal to form a larger nation, is closely linked to the history of modern Nepal. He ruled over all eastern Nepal and a huge part of present Sikkim between that time and his death in 1775. Following him, Rajendra Laxmi and Bahadur established a strong state in the Himalayan region with the support of warriors from Nepal. Nepal is one of the world’s most ethnically diverse nations. The issues of castes, classes, or communities in a nation building process become the part of state restructuring. The characteristics of Nepal, never colonized by an external power, are its diverse geography, ethnicity and religion. After killing innocent but brave Nepalese officials in Kot and Bhandarkhal in 1903 and getting political power from Surendra Bikram Shah, Jung Bahadur Rana initiated a despotic system. He had destroyed all of his main competitors and put his own candidate on the throne and all the key positions and made sure that he was the Prime Minister when it came to making important administrative decisions.1 King Surendra turned to be a rubber stamp of Rana regime whom the king had granted the power of the King of Lamjung and Kaski districts. For 104 years, Rana rulers practiced all executive powers including the appointment and dismissal of officials and the formulation of Nepalese laws to rule the country and it collapsed in only 1951.2

In Nepal, different political events occurred to dethrone Ranas and various political parties were established to institute democratic regime. In 1876, Lakhan Thapa Magar a native from Gorkha district led a systematic political revolt against the Rana rulers and organized local people to revolt against the regime to offer justice to the people. After 55 years of this unsuccessful move, another event of Prachanda Gorkha3 was established in 1931 to end the Rana regime and help weaken the root of despotic system through public awareness. Praja Parishad4 was established in 1936 to oust the Rana autocratic rule and the activists of this movement had appealed to the common people to fight for freedom, justice and human dignity. Deepak Thapa and Bandita Sijapati state, ‘Nepal Praja Parishad advocated reforms and fermented anti-establishment sentiments among the people. The Rana rulers quickly crushed the movement.’5 In 1937 the Nepalese Citizen Rights Committee was established to create awareness through pamphlets and articles. The political activists Sukharaj Shastri, Dharma Bhakta Mathema, Dasaratha Chanda and Ganga Lal Shrestha were killed in 1941.6 Jayatu Sanskritam movement of 1947 was followed by a group of students against the Rana regime. Pramode Shamshere J.B. Rana (1999) states that the protestors called for Jayatu Sanskritam.7 The students of the Tin Dhara Pathshala Sanskrit School in Kathmandu claimed democracy, basic welfare and the insertion of contemporary subjects in their curriculum and it was the first students’ political movement (Gautama, 2005), which supported the political movement of 1951.8

Political parties are imperative to the development of democracy and nation-building. Within the political system, they carry out different tasks. In addition to forming political opinions, they carry out some traditional duties like socialization, recruitment of officials, mobilization and mediation among agencies, the state and society. Political parties are receptive and accountable to society through these actions. As a means of nation-building, they also handle conflicts by providing a forum for social, cultural, political and economic integration. They strive for democracy, justice, equality, inclusion and political empowerment. In practice, political parties play a fundamental role within a well-functioning democracy, representing citizens’ interests and verbalizing policies that could support common people’s concerns. In the past, especially in developing countries like Nepal, political parties seemed disconnected from the policies to unite people. They pretended to have connected citizens’ interests with the political guidelines of the parties. In line with this, the Nepalese political parties, were formed to dismantle the repressive Rana family system and establish a democratic regime in Nepal.9

From the above historical perspective, different political movements initiated in Nepalese political history which was essential for setting up a representative democratic system. Hachhethu (2002) views that Nepalese political parties were organized and established ‘in opposition to the Rana oligarchy in the country,’10 and fought for making the people sovereign in history. NC aimed to establish democracy in Nepal—the party leaders were influenced by Indian political movement. Hachhethu (2002) states that the political base of the NC was the same as other political movements and opines, ‘Since the parties had emerged with a mission they had suffered from the lack of clarity of thought once their mission to bring an end to the Rana regime was fulfilled through the 1950-1-armed revolution’.11

The communist movement officially emerged in Nepal in 1949. Pushpa Lal Shrestha, a member of the NC, had quit the party and joined the communist movement. The party’s slogan, at the initial stage, was to fight for ‘civil liberties for all the classes’ was officially drawn from the guideline of Marxist political theory. The political circumstance of Nepal and structure of Nepali society justified that Nepal was a living reality to heighten the communist movement. Archie Brown (2010) views that Marx secretly thought that people would live more freely than ever under communism and the future society which he predicted as an inevitable stage for human development.12 Similarly, Hachhethu observes that although the political parties did not initially appear to be ideological groups when they were formed, the CPN adopted the readymade ideologies of Marxism and Leninism with the aim of overthrowing the despotic Rana rule and establishing democracy.13

After the end of the Rana regime, Nepalese political parties carried out political democratization and modernization through political education and by articulating public interest. However, in a short time, the political leaders appeared weak to maintain a dynamic leadership for sustaining democracy. Using the constitutional emergency power, King Mahendra seized political power over the State on 15 December 1960, claiming that the NC government, formed in 1959, had failed to uphold law and order, encouraged corruption and prioritized party politics over the interests of the country. The King imposed direct rule, adjourned the constitution, dissolved the elected parliament and the cabinet while imprisoning the then Prime Minister B.P. Koirala as well as his closest allies.14 The parties were forbidden to organize any activities. After the political coup d’état of 1960, he got a political space to introduce the party-less panchayat system in 1961.15 As the government was dissolved, Mahendra took over, imprisoning the opponents and establishing an authoritarian regime. He banned political parties outright in favour of a system without the existence of political parties as he believed that they contained antinational elements. In addition, he disapproved of and protested King Tribhuvan’s choice to recognize a democratic system and hold an election of constituent assembly.16 The political leaders, therefore, failed to consolidate the state, ‘a state in which the whole is greater than the sum of its parts’.17 Thereafter, political conflict intensified due to poverty and income inequality. From the beginning, all parties both the NC and the CPN experienced challenges with implementing intraparty democracy and improving the living standard of people. The main leaders chose to nominate the central working committees according to their ways, which ultimately weakened the ideological struggle within the parties. The undemocratic structure of the leading political parties hindered the equal participation of all strata of society further disadvantaging communities that had already been marginalized before the advent of democracy.

The involvement of marginalized groups in politics by the radical communists was a positive sign, garnering significant support from the common people. The poor oppressed politically and socially excluded individuals, along with women benefitted from the open-space programmes of the communists to articulate their aspirations, which helped expand their political programmes. Even the political movements of 1951 and 1990 failed to address the common desire of people. K.P. Malla (1973) argues that the political change of 1951 occurred within a definite political framework and parties had to outline democratic codes to govern the people. After 1951, in the post-democratic era, Nepali intellectuals explored political guidelines, emphasizing that the post-1950 decade was marked by an unprecedented proliferation of intellectual and cultural opportunities, replacing the traditional constraints with a new found liberation and intellect freedom. The decade from 1950 to 1960 is aptly referred to as an extroverted decade, marked by a plethora of ideas, events and coordinated endeavours.18

To settle the political issues and achieve the socio-economic progress in the country, the political parties are the main stake holders to implement good policies and set the required plans. However, the parties and the leaders failed to play a significant role which offered the space for political conflicts in different times. The NC holds the title of principal proponent of Nepal’s multiparty democracy because of its history of democratic struggle. Despite claiming to support democratic socialism, the NC has historically, supported liberal, centre-right policies. Despite its repeated setbacks by the monarchy in 1960 and 2002, as well as ongoing internal strife, it has played a vital role in Nepal’s political evolution establishing a secular and republican government. Although several NC leaders have voiced doubts about federalism and secularism, the party has shown flexibility since the 2006 transition and has, in theory, supported progressive agendas like positive discrimination for marginalized groups and proportional representation.

PARTY CULTURE AND IDEOLOGY

Based on a particular ideological worldview, the leaders mobilize their activists and common people within the party organization and craft new opportunities to rule the country. Every political party made up of a group of people stands unitedly to promote the national interest within a shared set of ideological principles. The agenda of political party celebrates the fact that the party building is for acknowledging its own socio-political goals to maximize intraparty democracy. The ideology of NC endorsed its guideline as ‘democratic socialism’ from its Birgunj party convention,19 and aimed to ameliorate for the effective development of the country. The slogan of CPN at its initial convention was ‘civil liberties for all classes’, with the idea of armed struggle clearly outlined. Some radical communists followed the same doctrine even after 1990, expressing their commitment to the belief that ‘Nepal should establish a new democracy as in China, if necessary through armed struggle, so as to create a People’s Republic’.20 For a long time, it remained a firm ideological doctrine of the Maoists and they accepted the principle to transform the country into a socialist state as Lenin had coined in Russia. Similarly, the present Constitution of Nepal (2015) affirms its commitment to socialist democratic norms and values.21

Even in 1984, the Royal Palace controlled Nepali politics and the country’s central government was disorganized while lacking a clear strategy. The political division between the hard-liner and liberal panchas,22 represented by Lokendra Bahadur Chanda and Surya Bahadur Thapa, deepened as dissatisfaction with the panchayat system grew.23 If such a political situation develops, the ideology of every political party becomes a governing principle from which the party advances its activities among the people. Ideology and party principles are the central aspects of political parties based on which they train their workers and get the support of the people to achieve their intended political goals. Politically, NC had a strong faith in a liberal economy and since its establishment a huge section of the middle-class people favoured its ideology. In contrast, the CPN brought the voices of the voiceless people, the landless, the oppressed and espoused rural agrarian struggle to fulfil the party mission. Yub Nath Lamsal writes, ‘It is the ideology and values that make a political party distinct and different from others.’24 Nepalese communist parties were established to make the people happier than before, and the first pamphlet of CPN accepted the same feeling. As the principle of Marxism states, ‘Karl Marx sincerely believed that under communism—the future society of his imagination which he saw as an inevitable and ultimate, stage of human development—people would live more freely than ever before.’25

The political identity of every political party is attached to the political guidelines. The credibility of the party remains among the people for a long, if the party’s ideology is shaped by political history, the missions of establishing the party, its objectives and the moral ethics of the leaders. The study of the political culture and ideology of NC and CPN shows that they were established with the same background but look different in their political doctrines. NC adopted democratic socialism whereas CPN’s party line embraced the global views of Marxist theory and its doctrine of class struggle. The available sources states that the political parties in Nepal had once again adopted the same political tactic to restore democracy in 1989-90. The coalition movement of Democratic Party NC, United Left Forum (ULF) and United National People’s Movement (UNPM)—a group of radical Communists succeeded in restoring democracy in Nepal after 30 years of absolute monarchical rule under the party-less panchayat system. Though NC and the Communist Parties had ideological differences, they united in their goal to liberate the country from an active monarchy. Together, the NC and ULF sought to construct a democratic system in 1990. However, Baburam Bhattarai led the UNPM, which was composed exclusively of ultra-left political groups, including the CPN (Mashal) under Prachanda and the CPN (Mashal) under Mohan Bikram Singh,26 both of which had adopted a comprehensive democratic agenda. After the formation of the interim government led by Krishna Prasad Bhattarai, the leader of NC in 1990, there was an understanding between NC and leaders of ULF to form a democratic constitution that had issued a directive to the interim government and stated that the King must be a constitutional monarch and act only on the advice of Council of Ministers. Their common agenda was the new constitution must be fully democratic and every law and institution that is in opposition to the democratic values needs to be changed. Every citizen must have access to democratic rights.27

Nepal’s political parties had an enormous task following the restoration of democracy in 1990 and the democratic movement successfully swapped the active panchayat system which had ruled Nepal for three decades. Restoring multiparty democracy, lifting the prohibition on political parties and curtailing rather than toppling the King’s authority were the goals of the 1990 pro-democratic movement. Only with the united action, the political parties could guarantee freedom and equality for all citizens, but it could not happen in practice. It was the main problem of Nepalese political parties that brought a political rift to fuel the grounds for radical communists. For the radical communist parties, the political movement of 1990 could not address the common political reality as it had accepted the political boundary of constitutional monarchy, it automatically widened the gap among the parties. G.P. Koirala, General Secretary of NC, remarked in a mass gathering in Kathmandu, stating that the objectives of the movement were to establish democracy and draft a new constitution, ultimately bringing an end to the constitutional monarchy. Since the King’s promises have been broken numerous times throughout history, NC ensured that these demands would be fulfilled this time. The leaders could only accomplish these objectives by remaining united.28

Even after the successful political movement of 1990, Nepal faced several hurdles in its ways and people experienced political crises that fuelled the ground for political insurgency. The Constitution of 1991 ignored the voices of common people and the left political parties. Lok Raj Baral (2004) compares the Nepali parliamentary system with the British system and concludes that Nepalese political leaders could not perform well for the people. He notes that the political power struggles of leaders among leaders have led to corruption, fostering an environment where corrupt practices can thrive in the pursuit of power. The likelihood of a stable government and its capacity to carry out policies in an environmentally sound manner have been significantly undermined by the power struggle. Instead of having meaningful and long-lasting policy measures, there have been frequent shifts in the rhetoric surrounding policies from one government to the next.29 Political party is a part of every modern society and it functions as a group of people organized to achieve constitutional objectives and defend the sovereignty of the people. In a multicultural country like Nepal, political parties play major roles to integrate the citizens and access them to the services of the governing institutions. Samuel P. Huntington observes, ‘The function of the party is to organize participation, to bring together separate interests and to serve as the link between social forces and government.’30

The CPN (Maoist) adopted the principles of Marxism, Leninism and Maoism as ideological guidelines of the party. After 1990, it regenerated its name from the CPN (Unity Centre) to CPN (Maoism) as its extended Congress decided to adopt ‘Marxism-Leninism-Maoism’ as the ‘ideological direction’ of the party. On 22 April 1949, the CPN(CPN) was established and the party accepted ‘agrarian revolution as the main policy revolution in Nepal’.31 Since the beginning, the CPN had adopted to establish ‘New People’s Republic Political System’ guided by the political doctrine of Mao Zedong—and the CPN (Maoist) followed the same guideline when it initiated a decade-long political movement in 1996. The first pamphlet of the CPN in 1949 acknowledged the necessity of launching an armed struggle as the people of Nepal fought for civil liberty through a revolutionary movement. Thus, it should not be restricted to protest using non-violence alone. The anti-people policies of the Rana oligarchy were boycotted by revolutionary committees for civil liberty in every village, town, district, school, college and factory. The party appealed to declare their laws and regulations, organize protests and meetings, seize control of multiple locations to address the demands of labourers, peasants and other workers.32

Political parties in every developing country grapple with peripheral political policies and when they do, it can foster consensus among them on major public issues. Social security, economy, health, education, transportation, communication, drinking water and delivery of basic public goods must be the parts of the common agenda for political parties. In Nepal, even after the political movement of 1990, establishing a consensus ruling parties was not a common goal. This lack of unity contributed to the rise in support for the radical communist party, which played a significant role in the political conflict of 1996. In this context, De Sales (2000) argues that the Maoists garnered support largely due to economic grievance, socio-political inequality and injustice.

POST-1990 COMMUNIST PARTIES IN NEPAL

There were many challenges before drafting the constitution in 1991 and a clear rift between left and right-wing political parties was observed. Since the political parties had their political demands they wanted to be incorporated into the Constitution of Nepal which pushed the political parties on different political grounds. Thapa and Sijapati (2006) state ‘. . . the left was not too happy about a constitution drawn up by a committee and had instated on an election to a constituent assembly, with the radical [political parties] from the UNPM raising up a chorus in support’.33 The promulgation of the new constitution of Nepal in 1991 had not brought political cheerfulness among the country’s different minority groups and radical communist parties which condemned the declaration of the constitution as their demands went politically unfulfilled. Nickson writes the structural problem of Nepalese politics fuelled the ground for radical communists to increase the political support of common people. He states that this process of political polarization is aided by the failure of the parliamentary system to bring about structural reform and the continued decline in the economic status of urban youth and the rural poor, even without any attempt by the monarchy to reclaim its authority. However, if the latter occurred, the message conveyed by Masal 34 regarding his disdain for the 1991 Constitution and the parliamentary democracy it established would undoubtedly gain new significance. These factors suggest that, in contrast to worldwide trends, Nepal’s medium-term Maoist prospects are far from exhausted.35

The CPN (Maoist) had already begun an open conflict in the rural districts of western Nepal especially in Rolpa and Rukum and according to the party ideology of ‘Marxism-Leninism-Maoism’, it was keen to implement the path of protracted people’s war. At that time, it mobilized the mass and embraced the revolutionary plan for Nepal. It shaped Nepal’s strategy and tactics during the People’s War in 1995—the party reaffirmed its unwavering commitment to theory of people’s war, developed by Mao as universal and unbeatable theory of warfare in China. The commitment was central to their historical initiation of people’s war, adopted by the CPN (Maoist) Central Committee in September 1995. This plan is based on the strategy for encircling the urban area from the countryside, tailored to the unique circumstances of our nation. On the other side, the CPN (United Marxist and Leninist) practiced open politics and participated in the government forum. People’s multiparty democracy was the NC’s political doctrine, and it ultimately agreed to reach a political understanding with the CPN (Maoist) for the peace process. Various political struggles, including those of 1968, the political movement of 1990, and the decade-long movement from 1996 to 2006—especially initiated by the CPN (Maoist) with a forty-point demand presented to the Government of Nepal in 1996—focused on achieving civil liberty through struggle.

The political history of Nepal is marked by various constitutional delays. For the first time, King Mahendra promulgated a new constitution at the beginning of 1959. Then, in 1990, King Birendra accepted constitutional change and it laid the ground for democracy. It accepted the multiparty democracy, with the King serving as Head of State and an executive Prime Minister. It could not endure the political system for a long time and the country experienced a decade long political conflict from 1996. The rise of Communism, even more than the rise of traditional Democratic Party, e.g. NC was the most important political phenomenon of the last decade of the twentieth century and the first decade of the twenty-first century turned out to be a much stronger and long lasting political movement in Nepal as the CPN (Maoist) initiated ‘People’s War’ in 1996. The twelve-point-understanding36 signed by the seven political parties and the Maoists, which preceded the Comprehensive Peace Agreement (CPA) 2006 pledged to uphold democracy and peace for the advancement of the nation and its citizens. The agreement was signed on 21 November 2006 by the Government of Nepal and CPN (Maoist). An interim constitution was also issued. On 20 September 2015, the new constitution of Nepal came into effect with a resounding majority of votes cast by CA members.37 Nepal’s parliamentary democracy faced Maoist’s decade-long political conflict during 1996-2006 and it was followed by the CPA 2006 alarmingly helped increase the supporters of communist groups. Maoist leaders had convinced the people that their demand for CA would offer all sorts of rights to the common people. From the election of the first CA to the present general election, communist parties got the support of rustic as well as urban people. Finally, the country was declared a Federal Democratic Republic, the 240-year-old monarchy was overthrown on 28 May 2008, when the recently elected CA proclaimed Nepal a Federal Democratic Republic.38 As assumed by the CPN (Maoist) before 1996, their leaders were moving ahead to fight for the people and they believed it would bring real political change in Nepal.

LEAP OF COMMUNISTS IN NEPAL

In the elections to the House of Representatives in 1991 and 1994 more than 33 per cent voters opted for the Communist Party. They received more than 60 per cent of the votes in the post-2008 elections. Even after the political movement of 1951 and general elections of 1958 the socio-economic structure of the country remained same and the feudal group was internally resilient. Due to the political coup by King Mahendra in 1961, the public’s perception towards the Communist Party turned positive. In 1963, the NC postponed the political struggle convened by Suvarna Shamser due to national and international political reasons, particularly the 1962 war between Nepal and China which increased the votes of the communists. The communist movement in Jhapa started in 197139 and got the support of Nepalese youths. However, due to the national reconciliation policy adopted by the NC in 1976, the policies of the NC became unattractive among the youths. Even the new constitution adopted in 1990 could not change the social and economic structure of Nepalese society, which fuelled the ground for communism in Nepal.40

The former CPN (Unity Center), which later became the CPN (Maoist), did not accept the constitution of 1990. The party used the first parliamentary election in 1991, based on the 1990 constitution, to subvert the political system. According to Lenin, new stages of revolution emerge from changes in the power balance at the international level.41 In 1996, the Maoist struggle took place at the same reality of Lenin’s understanding of political revolution. In order to get the people’s support for the movement from the stages of the revolution, the United People’s Front had submitted forty-point-demand to the government of Nepal in 1996.42 The leftist political parties in Nepal always focused on the issues of revolution, political guidelines, struggle and transformation of society and connected events like nationality, e.g. the Mahakali Treaty, the killing of the royal family in the palace and the demand of people’s rights. Before the 19-day movement in 2006, seven-political-party and the Maoist agreed to hold the round-table conference, announcement of the Interim Constitution and a new constitution drafted and promulgated by the Constituent Assembly got people’s verdict in 2008 to receive great support from the Nepalese people.43 The proclamation of the new constitution by the Constituent Assembly in 2015 and the 2017 elections made Nepal’s communists a strong political force, but they failed to use the people’s vote.

The history of Nepal’s Communist Parties is factionalism.44 However, they drew the attraction of huge number people in their political organizations and justified that they would be a power centre to change the society.45 Nepal’s peace process was theoretically initiated in 2005 after the signing on the 12-point understanding between the political parties and in Nepalese politics it was a turning point in the history of Nepali politics. Members of civil society, human rights workers and the political leaders of Nepal played a positive role in initiating the dialogue among the parliamentary parties and rebel groups. Even after the initiation of the peace process in Nepal and during the time of both elections of the Constituent Assembly, CPN (Maoist) frequently used it for the new people’s movement to bring to a logical end of bringing political achievement in Nepal through the peace process. In a press statement, the leaders announced that the nation now demands that the armed conflict can be resolved amicably and that a lasting peace be established. Therefore, the party is fully committed to ending the autocratic monarchy, holding elections for the Constituent Assembly and ending the current armed conflict through a progressive political outlet with the establishment of a full-fledged democracy to bring about permanent peace.46

The political agreement made an understanding to integrate the combatants into Nepalese security forces. It was the victory of Maoists that helped justify their political movement as the previous political movements of Nepal that occurred in 1951 and 1990 failed to address the people’s demands. The interesting and unique part of the peace process was the initiation of an open fight between the parliamentary political parties and the Maoists against the monarchical political system of Nepal. After signing the 12-point-agreement, the seven political parties agreed to construct a new political alliance between the seven political parties and the rebel forces that aimed to establish a federal republic country. Ian Martin (2012) acknowledges, ‘The 12-point understanding had included the commitment to international supervision of the two armies during the election.’47 As this, the decade-long political uprising brought some structural changes in legal statutes to mark the socio-economic transformation of Nepal. Earlier, Nepalese intellectuals were the political opponents of Maoists as they had a fear of its political doctrine. Despite that assumption, Maoists were politically admired by many people as they contributed to bringing about many social reforms and changes. In the past, several women, indigenous groups, Madhesi and Dalits were under socio-cultural domination as they felt political marginalization. The Maoists recruited thousands of women in their people’s liberation army and it forced the government to recruit women in Nepalese security forces. Baral (2007) considers that Maoist’s principle based on Marxist, Leninist and Maoist is redefined to practice in Nepalese context. He further said the Maoists were flexible enough to accept a multi-party system and pluralistic society, which made them compatible to cooperate with the other bourgeois parties. In the first general elections of 1959, CPN had bagged only 4 seats out of 109 whereas Communists got 61.5 per cent votes in the first CA of 2008. After the announcement on new Constitution in 2015, all at once, two largest Communist Parties, i.e. CPN (UML) and CPN (Maoist Center) made a political alliance for the election in 2017 and got 63.27 per cent seats in the Federal Parliament. The decade-long insurgency spawned a political climate that brought about changes in legal statutes, marking socio-economic transformation. In the political arena, it summed up the lived experience of progress for marginal groups from a bottom-up approach, leading to a substantial political shift and the establishment of new power relations. The present Constitution of Nepal endorses a commitment to socialism based on democratic norms and values,48 reflecting the current ideological and cultural principles of the Nepalese Communist Party.

COMMUNIST PARTIES AT PRESENT

The new post-conflict constitution has fulfilled the expectations of people, which were earlier overlooked in the 1991 constitution. It has set out an overhaul of the political system, devolving significant power from the centre to the seven provinces. People now perceive this as a political tactic of the Maoists, who ultimately succeeded in forming the largest ruling communist party in Nepal. The new party follows the ideological philosophy of Marxism–Leninism, with its political line centred on‘People’s Democracy’. Their merger to become the Nepal Communist Party has gained political momentum in the country, making it easier to address the people’s agenda. Adhikari (2014) states, ‘The large proportion of Maoist rank and file belonged to historically marginalized caste and ethnic groups’49 and with the support of marginal groups, poor people and women, Maoists (Communist) gained popularity in Nepalese politics.

Democracy is always for the happiness of people and every political movement should be for bringing changes in the country. The two remaining communist parties, CPN (UML) and UCPN (Maoist) formed a Left Political Alliance to contest in the recently concluded elections for Nepal’s parliament and provincial assemblies. They bagged nearly two-thirds of the seats in the 275-member Federal Parliament and formed governments in six out of seven provincial assemblies. The Left Alliance theoretically was an unexpected coalition between Maoist and Marxist-Leninist parties and now the communist movement in Nepal is facing a crisis as they are not in the same position. The constitutional announcement and the general elections of 2017 politically ended an eleven-year transition from monarchy to federal democracy after a brutal civil war between Maoists and the state. The election is the symbol of the country’s socio-political transformation and is an objective of a decade-long conflict. However, the fundamental issue of peace process, i.e. the cases of victims is still unresolved.

After ending the civil war, holding the election of constituent assembly and three levels elections in 2017 and 2022, Nepalese left politics have entered to new phase. Political ideology is shifted to democratic values and norms. The positive development in Nepalese politics has brought sound prospects for strengthening democracy in Nepal. The future course of democratization in Nepal will be measured as a successful tactic if the left political parties uplift the lives of the poor and transform the Nepali economy into a prosperous one. However, the communist parties typically start out with radical and revolutionary rhetoric before gradually transitioning to a social democratic paradigm. Eventually, even the parties that persist in supporting revolutionary socialism will turn into a space for neo-bourgeoisies. The two most powerful moderate communist parties now are UML and Maoist Center, in the realm of legislative politics, these parties are fighting for a position and now they are experiencing an existential dilemma. In Nepali politics, triangle polarization means that there will not be two powerful, moderate communist parties for a very long time. Since one of UML and the Maoist Center will undoubtedly merge. The political coalition between Maoist Center and UML in 2017 was a part of rebirth of communist movement in Nepal and their rift in 2021 was a part of crisis in ideology.

CONCLUSION

Nepalese Communists have achieved significant success in global politics. The promulgation of the Nepalese constitution through CA and inclusion of combatants in security forces legitimized their political agenda of equality, justice, freedom, inclusion and empowerment. By adopting Maoist principles alongside leftist social democratic ideology and transitioning from a decade-long political struggle to the practice of a parliamentary system, they gained widespread popularity at the ballot box. Their experiences from violent war to the peace process, have demonstrated the political struggle of Communists of Nepal in all forms of struggle. This identity of Communists in Nepal remained strong for good reasons. The Maoist Party, an isolated faction of the CPN, was not popular among intellectuals as other political parties of Nepal before 1990. Its regular movement vowed to stand up for the rights of people who were politically voiceless and deprived among others. The Maoist insurgency gradually expanded across the country and finally succeeded in uniting with the next largest communist party is itself a historical move to get the huge support of the Nepalese people. Though, NC had the goal of multiparty democracy, it failed to grasp the support of poor people and stood second in the elections of 2017.

To explore the history of socialism as outlined in the Constitution of Nepal, Nepalese political parties must unite. Now is a time to follow the principles of people’s participation in every sector of citizen’s lives and implement the constitution in practice. From this analysis, the best conclusion is that Nepalese people got many things for the first time in history that should be sustainable to reconcile Nepalese politics in a post-conflict country like Nepal. If the political leaders of Nepal work to lead the country toward economic development, the model of peace process could serve as an asset for other countries that have experienced prolonged political conflict. The rise of Communists in Nepal and their support for communist ideology aim to prevent future conflicts. However, Nepali people have endured a long political transition and Nepalese political parties failed to bring the peace process into a logical conclusion risks plunging the country back into a dark future. The rise of the Communists in Nepal during the 2017 elections positioned them as a mainstream political actor, with the expectation of governing for five years by a single political party. Voting for the communists was perhaps a means for political stability and economic prosperity aligning with the promises made by the Left Alliance UML-Maoists before the elections. However, the current communist movement in Nepal is in crisis and to avoid this political dilemma the Maoist Center and UML are likely to unite.

NOTES

1. Welpton, A History of Nepal, xi.

2. Singh, ‘Rise and Growth of Anti Rana Movement in Nepal’, 992.

3. First political party of Nepal established to overthrow the Rana regime.

4. The first political party of Nepal.

5. Thapa and Sijapati, A Kingdom under Siege: Nepal’s Maoist Insurgency, 1990 to 2004, 14.

6. Welpton, A History of Nepal, xii.

7. Victory to the cause of Sanskrit.

8. Snellinger, Making New Nepal: From Student Activism to Mainstream Politics, 35-6.

9. Welpton, A History of Nepal, 86.

10. Hachhethu, Party Building in Nepal, 1.

11. Ibid., 1.

12. Brown, The Rise and the Fall of Communism, 9.

13. Hachhethu, Party Building in Nepal, 1.

14. Nepal’s Cabinet is Ousted by King; Mahendra Seizes Ministers as ‘Anti-Nationalists’ and Dissolves Parliament. The New York Times, 16 December 1960.

15. Constitution of Nepal, 1962.

16. King Tribhuvan was committed to hold the election for Constituent Assembly to draft the Constitution but died in 1954.

17. Grimond, Splitting Image, 29.

18. Malla, ‘The Intellectual in Nepalese Society’, 227.

19. Siwakoti, ed., Democracy and Socialism: Thoughts of BP Koirala, 197-8.

20. Karki and Seddon, The People’s War in Nepal: Left Perspectives, 6.

21. Constitution of Nepal, 2015.

22. The supporters of Panchayat system are called panchas.

23. Tiwari, 1985 Yearbook on International Communist Affairs, 220.

24. Lamsal, Ideological Deviation in Politics.

25. Brown, The Rise and Fall of Communism, 9.

26. Before 1990 NC and the parties included under the banner of United Left Forum agreed to established constitutional democracy. In the same time radical communist parties involved in UNPM had demanded republican system in Nepal.

27. Hutt, ‘Drafting the 1990 Constitution’, 32.

28. Hoftun, Raeper and Whelpton, People, Politics and Ideology, 134.

29. Baral, ‘Nepal Political Parties and Parliament’, 36.

30. Huntington, ‘Democracy for the Long Haul’, 67.

31. Sapkota, Ten Years of Upheaval, 15.

32. Shrestha, Short History of Communist Movement in Nepal, 37-8.

33. Thapa and Sijapati, A Kingdom under Siege: Nepal’s Maoist Insurgency, 1990 to 2004, 34.

34. CPN (Mashal) was changed into CPN (Unity Center) in 1991 and finally it renamed as CPN (Maoist).

35. Nickson, ‘Democratization and the Growth of Communism in Nepal: A Peruvian Scenario in the Making’, 15.

36. Seven Political Parties and Nepal Communist Party (Maoist) agreed that the National Army and the Maoist Army would be under the supervision of the UN to conduct fair elections of CA and to accept international mediation.

37. Ministry of Foreign Affair, Kathmandu.

38. Ibid.

39. A conflict between landowners and tenants was announced by then King Mahendra in 1964. The Jhapa Rebellion was a peasant uprising that took place in the Jhapa district of Nepal in 1969.

40. Giri, ‘A Leap of Six Decades’, 20-5.

41. Lenin, Left-Wing Communism: An Infantile Disorder.

42. Thapa and Sijapati, A Kingdom under Siege: Nepal’s Maoist Insurgency, 1990 to 2004.

43. Giri, ‘A Leap of Six Decades’, 20-5.

44. Khadka, ‘Factionalism in the Communist Movement in Nepal’.

45. Tiwari, 1985 Yearbook on International Communist Affairs, 246.

46. Sapkota, Ten Years of Upheaval, 234-5.

47. Ian Martin, ‘The United Nations Support to Nepal’s Peace Process: The Role of the UN Mission in Nepal’, 205.

48. Constitution of Nepal, 2015.

49. Adhikari, The Bullet and the Ballot Box: The Story of Nepal’s Maoist Revolution, xii.

REFERENCES

Adhikari, Aditya (2014), The Bullet and the Ballot Box: The Story of Nepal’s Maoist Revolution. New Delhi: Rupa Publication.

Baral, Lok Raj (2004), ‘Nepal Political Parties and Parliament.’ In The Unclear Roadmap: Parties and the Parliamentary Process. New Delhi: Adroit Publications.

——(2007), ‘Prachanda on Prachanda Doctrine.’The Kathmandu Post, 9 May.

Brown, Archie (2009), The Rise and Fall of Communism. New York: Harper Collins.

Constitution of Nepal (1962), Kathmandu, Nepal.

Constitution of Nepal (2015), Kathmandu: Government of Nepal.

De Sales, A. (2000), ‘The Kham Magar Country, Nepal: Between Ethnic Claims and Maoism’. European Bulletin of Himalayan Research, 19, Autumn, pp. 1-24.

Giri, Pradip. ‘A Leap of Six Decades’. Nepal: National Daily, 2013.

Gupta, Bikash (2021), ‘One Hat To Rule Them All: The Dhaka Topi And The Subjugation Of Minority Cultures In Nepal’. www.recordnepal.com, Retrieved 1 July 2021.

Grimond, John (2015), ‘Splitting Images,’The Economist, The World in 2015.

Hachhethu, Krishna (2002), Party Building in Nepal: Organization, Leadership and People. Kathmandu: Mandala Book Point.

——(2006), ‘Political Parties of Nepal’, Social Science Baha. Retrieved on 11 June 2018. www.soscbaha.org/book/fbook/.../88.

——(2009), The CPN (Maoist): Transformation from an Insurgency Group to a Competitive Political Party, EBHR, 33-34: pp. 39-71.

Hoftun, Martin, William Raeper and John Whelpton (1999). People, Politics and Ideology. Kathmandu: Mandala Book Point.

Huntington, Samuel (1996), ‘Democracy for the Long Haul.’ Journal of Democracy.

Hutt, Michael (2001), ‘Drafting the 1990 Constitution’, Nepal in the Nineties. New Delhi: Oxford University Press, 2001.

Karki, Arjun and David Seddon, eds. (2003), The People’s War in Nepal: Left Perspectives. New Delhi: Adroit Publications.

Khadka, Narayan (1995), Factionalism in the Communist Movement in Nepal, Pacific Affairs, University of British Columbia, vol. 68, no. 1: pp. 55-76.

Lamsal, Yuba Nath (2017), Ideological Deviation in Politics. Retrieved on 12 June 2018. http://therisingnepal.org.np/news/14941.

Lenin, V. (1920). Left-Wing Communism: An Infantile Disorder. London.

Malla, K.P. (1973), ‘The Intellectual in Nepalese Society.’Nepal in Prosperity, ed. Pashupati Shamser Rana and Kamal Prakash Malla. Kathmandu: CEDA, 263-90.

Martin, Ian (2012), ‘The United Nations Support to Nepal’s Peace Process: The Role of the UN Mission in Nepal’. In Nepal in Transition: From People’s War to Fragile Peace, Eds. S.V. Einsidel, D.M. Malone and S. Pradhan. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2012.

Nickson, R. Andrew (1992), ‘Democratisation and the Growth of Communism in Nepal: A Peruvian Scenario in the Making?’ Journal of Commonwealth and Comparative Politics, vol. 30, no. 3: pp. 358-86.

Rana, Pramode Shamshere J.B. (1999), A Chronicle of Rana Rule. Michigan: The University of Michigan.

Sapkota, Dipak (2010), Ten Years of Upheaval: Reportage of the Decade Long Maoist People’s War in Nepal. Kathmandu: Revolutionary Journalist Association.

Shrestha, Puspalal (1997), Short History of Communist Movement in Nepal. Kathmandu: Puspalal Memorial Academy.

Singh, Chandra Prasad Singh (2004), ‘Rise and Growth of Anti Rana Movement in Nepal’, Jostor, vol. 65: pp. 992-1002.

Siwakoti, M.P. (ed.) (2022), Democracy and Socialism: Thoughts of B.P. Koirala. Kathmandu: Madhuvan Publication.

Snellinger, Amanda Therese (2018), Making New Nepal: From Student Activism to Mainstream Politics. Washington: University of Washington Press.

Spiess, Clemens (2009), Democracy and Party Systems in Developing Countries: A Comparative Study of India and South Africa, London: Routledge.

Thapa, Deepak & Bandita Sijapati (2006), A Kingdom under Siege: Nepal’s Maoist Insurgency, 1996 to 2003. Kathmandu: The Print House.

Tiwari, C.K. (1985), 1985 Yearbook on International Communist Affairs, Ed. Richard F. Staar, California: Hoover Institution Press.

——(1989), 1989 Yearbook on International Communist Affairs, Ed. Richard F. Staar, Hoover Institution Press, California.

Whelpton, John (2005), A History of Nepal. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

Wild, Leni Wild & Jiwan Subedi (2010), ‘Review of International Assistance to Political Party and Party System Development: Case Study Report—Nepal’ London: Overseas Development Institute. Retrieved on 6 June 2018 https://www.odi.org/sites/odi.org.uk/files/odi-assets/publications-opinion-files/6873.pdf

CHAPTER 2

Post-Conflict Political Participation
of Women in Nepal

SARMILA BAGALE

HISTORICAL OVERVIEW OF NEPALESE WOMEN

The total population of Nepal as of 2021 was 29,164,578, with females comprising 51.13 per cent, which is slightly higher than the number of males.1 The present Constitution of Nepal 2015 AD has guaranteed some specific provisions to offer certain political rights to women. It has acknowledged, ‘Every woman shall have equal lineage right without gender-based discrimination’, Article 38 and Article 38(5) accepts that [Nepalese] women have obtained special privileges in education, health, employment, social security, etc., to empower the women for making positive changes in their lives.2

Historically, Nepal, a Himalayan country, emerged as a unified state, the Kingdom of Gorkha Shah dynasty, which governed the Kathmandu valley. This region has a long history, with over 2,000 years of civilization. From the beginning to the emerging Shah dynasty, there was a very strong influence of Hindu patriarchal mindset in the Nepalese political system that continuously marginalized the women in the political system. Nepal is a culturally diverse country and Hindu religion played a significant role in shaping Nepalese society; and only the promulgation of Interim Constitution in 2006 changed in this provision.3 In a patriarchal society, like Nepal, the relationship between male and female is formed by religious ideologies.4 Hinduism has been a way of life for Nepalese people as majority of people follow this religion. It shapes the socio-cultural values in Nepalese society. R. Stump (2008) asserts that religion is deeply ingrained in peoples’ experiences and behaviours which stimulates the socio-economic and political dynamics of societies.5 In both the modern Western worldview, and in Nepal, religion shapes human perspective and influences the control of societal events.

Different perspectives of religion play a dominant role in shaping social system, e.g. substantive view of religion entails it as a system of culturally experiencing the way of life and its practices lean towards cultural dominion of people. The functional view of religion establishes powerful constant moods and motivations in people’s mind to develop conceptions of a general order of existence. In this way, male domination in Nepalese society—despite the higher female population—is reflected in national policy. B.N. Adams and R.A. Sydie (2009) note that Western religion stems from a patriarchal worldview, resulting in patriarchal domination across all sectors.6 In line with this, A. Sachedina (2003) remarked that women were historically denied fundamental human rights as a result of economic manipulation and exploitation of their position in the family and society.7 Unlike this, the revolt of Yogmaya Neupane—a common Brahmin widowed-woman gave voices to the voiceless women, had married thrice when widow marriage was a deplorable offence in Nepalese society. It was an offence against religious values of Hindu socio-politico-cultural system that inspired Nepalese women to stand for their own future and fight against sexual discrimination. Her movement from traditional social beliefs to modern ways of thinking was an initiation of new threat to patriarchal political power system of Nepal.8

Michael Foucault (1981) states that the theoretical modality of political exclusion of women is a part of political ideas that intends to subordinate the females in social sector. For him, the notion of political exclusion of women leads to marginalization in socio-political sector. The emergence of exclusionary institutions is accompanied by the formation of scientific language that incorporates the idea of exclusion. He discusses exclusion and exclusionary procedures, whereby in every society the use of discourse is simultaneously managed, chosen, arranged and redistributed by a number of procedures whose purpose is to avoid its formidable, ponderous materiality, to gain control over its chance events and to fend off its powers and dangers.9 S. Bem (1994) frameworks three elementary assumptions that shape the cultural understandings of human beings that make a difference between males and females. The hypotheses are ‘andocentric’, ‘gender polarization’ and ‘biological essentialism’.10 The androcentric assumption always places male at the centre and female at the periphery. The gender polarization reinforces the idea that male and female are socially different while biological essentialism is emphasized as the most important aspect of the society. In this context, the situation of women in Nepal is not different to other places and politics is a power device to shape and lead the society and other existing institutions for peace, participation and development. As everywhere, in Nepal women are holding less political power compared to their male counterparts and have occupied less political space to govern the country. One of the major reasons behind it is a patriarchal mindset that has created structural discrimination against women to create socio-economic barrier which is part of the political system for the meaningful sharing of power for the women in politics.

Nepalese society has differently structured the gender relations, in which women are seen to be predominantly cooking, cleaning and rearing children. Nepalese women, as in most of the countries, had very pathetic and terrible life. They were living with double exploitation of class and gender. In addition, child marriage, polygamy and forced marriage were prevalent in Nepalese society. Punam Yadav has analysed the condition of Nepalese women from the perspective of social transformation and views that the social realities and religious beliefs construct the political framework.11 Bourdieu and Nice elucidate how masculine domination influences the structures of the political system. The social world view is always perceived by males as market goods for women.12 As we have argued here religious social structure is based on masculine world view which since long had curbed the political desire of Nepalese women, since the state culture is viewed as a social structure ruled by male principles. To justify it, the fundamental myth creates an opposition between nature and culture, or more specifically, between nature’s sexuality and society’s sexuality. The act of anomie, which is performed next to the fountain, the epitome of the feminine and was instigated by the woman, the perverse seductress, who was naturally knowledgeable about matters of love, contrasts with the act of nomos, which is domesticated and domesticated, performed at the behest of man and adhering to the order of things, fundamental hierarchy of the social order and cosmic order.13 R. Eyben (2010) describes political empowerment as ‘people’s capacity to influence policy, make demands and call to account the state institutions that impact upon their lives. This includes political representation and collective action’.14 In many public spheres and across all geographic regions, women continue to face severe discrimination because of their involvement in public and political life. The under representation of women in positions of authority and decision-making has many intricate and varied causes. In addition to negative stereotypes about women and ingrained gender roles, economic, social and cultural issues also pose significant barriers to women’s involvement in public and political situations. The question of how gender is constituted differently in public and private spaces is central to the conceptualization of gender discrimination in the public domain. Feminist academics have been attempting to eliminate the barrier between public and private space for more than twenty years.15

WOMEN AFTER 1951 TO 1996

Two expected and highly ambitious plans were framed after the downfall of Rana regime that had ruled Nepal for 104 years. Deepak Thapa and Bandita Sijapati (2006) assert that King Tribhuvan had given a historic speech on 18 February 1951 and the monarch had declared his intention and choice to draft a democratic constitution by a constituent assembly.16 This political shift of 1951 was a major political movement in Nepalese political history to protect the rights of the people in different fields. Even after the end of Rana regime, during the first democratic period (1951-61), the socio-political sphere of women in Nepal was not remarkably good and authoritative patriarchal domination still played in their lives. Women’s political participation and inclusion in policy making level even in Panchayat regime (1961-90)17 remained too thin and this non-democratic system could not bring any policy to change in the existing system. It failed to draw the devotion to macro policies of development for women’s participation in politics and economic sectors. The political game of exclusion was practiced again, often in these same places and for the same reason—to make women weaker in politics and social sectors.

The Panchayat system had institutionalized the privileges of Kathmandu-elites that only prioritized the patriarchal system and ultimately it had marginalized the women. In Nepalese political history, the cultural understanding of male and female is different and is constructed by religious ideologies. Religious and cultural factors had placed the males at the centre and as Yadav writes until 2006 Hinduism was a dominant religious ideology in Nepal18 and only the Interim Constitution 2007 had accepted Nepal as a secular country. The political movement of 1990 was an end of Panchayat system that reinstated a multi-party democratic system and brought a little change in political ideology. However, the new Constitution in 1991 failed to address the political problems of Nepalese women and they felt no substantial changes in their political career. It failed to make a good progress on people’s participation in structural politics of Nepal. Catinca Slavu (2012) views that the failure of social inclusion to a large extent was a consequence of insufficient changes in the 1991 constitution and it maintained key exclusionary features reaffirming Nepal as a Hindu state and maintaining highly centralized state structures.19 It had created a gap between the constitution, rhetoric and gender equality within Nepalese politics. The 1991 Constitution of the Kingdom of Nepal, called for the political parties to reserve at least 5 per cent candidature for women and made the assurance of 5 per cent women’s representation in parliamentary system. The following subsequent national elections in 1991, 1994 and 1999 resulted in only 5 per cent and 6 per cent and 9 per cent of women’s representation in parliament through election. These figures demonstrate women’s representation in parliament increased on average by only 4 per cent.20

B.R. Upreti (2008) states that ‘with the success of the democratic struggle of 1990, political awareness among Nepalese people had increased tremendously and their expectations with new government were much higher than in the past. However, the government failed to introduce good policies to fulfil the commitments’21 and Yadav adds that the Government of Nepal slackened to bridge the gap between haves and have-nots and eliminating inequality based on caste, ethnicity, gender, religion, region and sex which encouraged the Maoists to lead the new movement for establishing new social system based on their leftist ideology.22 The basic feature of women in democratic system of governance, even after the political changes of 1991, their participation and access to policy-making level was quite negligible. The Fourth World Conference on Women, held in Beijing in 1995 had focused on women’s participation in all the decision-making levels around the world. In Nepal, women’s participation in legislative, judiciary and executive were not felt important. It has thus become difficult for women to break from the vicious circle of poverty and disempowerment. Women were economically and politically disadvantaged due to their exclusion from the public domain and lack of public involvement.

Unlike this, Tulsi Acharya (2017) assumes that, after avoiding the constitution of 1991 by Maoists, Nepalese women’s participation in political movements made them politically, socially and culturally conscious. It acknowledged the changes in their traditional ways of thinking to move ahead in the political history. Their encouraging participation in the political movement persuaded them to challenge the social, cultural and religious practices that had marginalized them for centuries. Once more, the study indicates that women’s access to positions of political and administrative decision-making has been limited because of social expectations regarding their exclusive household responsibilities, limited mobility relative to men and limited access to economic and educational resources. The women’s movement in Nepal after 1990 is shaped by many political forces and ideological perspectives and is ingrained in the country’s political history. The constitution of 1990 had opined that ‘Nepal is a multi-ethnic, multi-lingual, democratic, independent, sovereign, Hindu, constitutional, monarchical kingdom’ and guaranteed fundamental rights to all citizens without discrimination based on ethnicity, caste, religion or sex.23

The political leaders had openly expressed the constitution to be ‘the best constitution in the world’. However, the constitution had offered the king as the central authority and finally the constitution failed to incorporate many demands of common people, women, etc. A unified women’s movement cannot emerge in a society that is driven by other hierarchical distinctions; it can only do so in tandem with the removal of other social bases of subordination aside from gender, despite the need for one being so obvious. This is why the most common catchphrase among Nepalese women activists even today is the lack of a certain political understanding. Secondly, attempts to enhance women’s status via associations and campaigns that are inexorably influenced by other societal divisions could unintentionally or intentionally hinder the development of a cohesive women’s movement.24 Therefore, Nepalese women had realized the importance of power politics and got the ideas of power and its legitimacy in politics that had reshaped their mind to build the ideas of political authority. Without getting political power, social transformation for Nepalese women was not possible.

NEPALESE WOMEN IN CONFLICT

The failure of the constitution of Nepal was the basic point for the Maoists to wage a decade long conflict. They began the protest in 1996 and many women from rural area were involved in the rebellion. The women, then, played the roles in the militia, cultural group, joined to play active role in the Maoists’ army and in the political wing of the party. They got actively involved in politics to get their political rights. Women mostly followed Marxism, Leninism and Maoism (MLM) ideology, which in turn inspired them to be fully free from patriarchal domination. Before 1996, there was a growing recognition of political discrimination against women based on gender, class, and sex. In fact, there was a strong desire for social transformation across the regions of the country to permanently improve the condition of women. The CPN (Maoist) had expressed its firm commitment about ending patriarchal exploitation and gender discrimination and giving the right of granting parental property to daughters.25 Similarly, Sierra Tamang agrees that among the many actors in the women’s movement in Nepal after 1990s, the CPN-M has received the most attention. The majority of writing about the ‘People’s War’ in Nepal by foreign and domestic journalists has included images of young and armed guerrilla women, wearing combat fatigues along with claims that between 30 per cent and 50 per cent of women participated in the conflict.26 Hisila Yami (2007) concedes that the strategy of incorporating women into the people’s army from the beginning has raised socio-political awareness, forcing the political parties of Nepal to recognize the need of addressing women’s political demands which highlights the unique nature of the People’s War.

The socio-political position of Nepalese women was shaped by political structure of the country which was prevalent at a political and socio-cultural level. The fundamental problems which have exploited the women as the second type of citizen was reflected in the context of Nepalese politics before the initiation of Maoist’s movement were stronger than at present time were the exploitation in social sector and marginalization. Nepalese cultural imperialism and violence were of the same patriarchal domination. Before 1996 the women who had ideological influence of MLM had observed much discrimination and involvement in politics to get political freedom. In a short time, as Sharma and Prasain (2004) write that the number of Maoists cadres gradually increased to 30 per cent to 40 per cent, attracting common people. They affirm that women have taken up a variety of roles, including those of nurses, couriers, organizers and even fully-fledged guerrilla combatants.27 The scholars have written that the women involved in Maoist movement were radical and CPN (Maoist) always advocated assuring rights for women, especially the working-class women. Yami (2006) writes Nepalese women became professionals in the revolution by joining People’s Liberation Army, militias and production brigades. Women were instructed to target the feudal state apparatus as a means of combating class and gender oppression following the start of the Maoist struggle. For the first time, they were actively organized in villages against the landlord, patriarchal customs, superstitions and socio-cultural stigmata.

This political movement of 2006 gave women political power to make choices and guaranteed them a crucial role in legislature after the initiation of the peace process. Nepalese women were essential political and cultural activists throughout a ten-year political battle. They had even participated in the military operations of the rebels. Women who were family members of the security forces’ were slained, raped, tortured and imprisoned throughout the fighting. The battle caused immense suffering to the spouses, mothers and daughters of men who were slained, disappeared, or subjected to torture. In addition to providing for their families’ needs, they also had to fulfil social and economic obligations. Some women were involved in combat as well. From a philosophical perspective, the ten-year conflict in Nepal is seen as a catalyst for the socio-political inclusion of women, initiating structural changes within the political strata. This shift has transformed the concept of political realization into an understanding of the historical systems of political guidelines. In this regard, the Maoist movement in Nepal represented a significant political turn for bringing equality of women across social classes while advancing their professional and political prospects. It truly brought major changes in political and economic sectors for women, assisting in their empowerment in Nepal.

The Interim Constitution of Nepal (2007) sufficiently addressed gender and women’s rights and, for the first time in Nepal’s political history, recognized women as equal citizens to men. This legal provision brought significant changes, supporting women’s empowerment and increasing their political participation in Nepalese politics. Regarding ‘Citizenship’, the Interim Constitution of Nepal (2007) approved the following provisions: no sex discrimination; employment and social security rights; women’s rights; right to social justice; right against exploitation; and equality between men and women. The Constitution of 2015 reaffirms this in Article (11)(2)(b) stating that a person whose father or mother was a citizen of Nepal at their birth is entitled to citizenship by descent. This marked the first-time women were empowered in this way. However, as Susan Risal writes in The Himalayan, a major English newspaper, women wounded by conflict are battling both external and internal traumas. To help them mend their wounds and rehabilitate them in society with dignity, the state and the transitional justice systems must put in an effort. These women deserve justice, but they also deserve to live honourable lives. Despite these facts, the Interim Constitution incorporated some specific provisions to provide political support to women. The government set up provisions for women’s political participation and constitutionalized it. Women’s participation in politics through election processes to carry out the Constitution and their growing voice is marked and the ‘yes we can do’, mentality is predicted to contribute to equality and success in the economy as well. Empowerment analysis must consider women’s engagement in public and political life in addition to their access to and mobilization within official and informal political venues. Political empowerment is no longer limited to the official sphere, which includes political parties and elections. It now faces additional obstacles as it must operate in entirely uncharted public and political areas regarding the strength of regional to international alliances, the voices and influence of women and innovative approaches to accountability. This paper sheds light on the ways in which the formal and informal converge, emphasizing these novel perspectives on public and political life and demonstrating how state-society connections might generate avenues for the advancement of gender equality objectives.

WOMEN IN POST-CONFLICT NEPAL

The initiation of peace process and promulgation of Interim Constitution were the consequences of a decade long conflict and the peaceful political movement of 2006. The first historic election of the Constituent Assembly in 2008 brought significant change in the pattern of gender equality. Women’s representation in the Legislature Parliament increased dramatically to 33 per cent placing Nepal sixteenth out of 140 countries in terms of the percentage of women in national parliament, down from sixty-eight in 1999. According to Tamang Sierra, the people’s movement of April 2006 exerted unprecedented pressure on the re-established parliament through the large-scale participation of women from excluded populations from urban to rural areas.28 The most positive part of Nepali peace process that was framed after 2006 had accepted the principle of socio-political transformation of Nepalese people including women. It was against traditional thinking that had aimed to liberate Nepalese women from age long traditional method of production and way of life. In Schlitz’s views a traditional society always accepts traditional values while a modern political world view always accepts the capacity of changing the society, inclusion of women in politics and finally making social transformation for peace and sustainable development. Nepalese Civil War that lasted for a decade was followed by the initiation of peace process and the election for the Constituent Assembly for drafting a constitution for Nepalese people. 32.8 per cent of Nepali women were elected as legislators in the voting system in 2008, which included a proportional system. This represents a significant improvement above the 5.8 per cent of women elected in 1999. According to K. Bhattarai and D. Budd (2008), Nepal became the region’s leader in female representation overnight when one-third of the elected parliamentarians were female.29

The Constitution of Nepal 2015 aims to end ‘all forms of discrimination and oppression created by the feudalistic, autocratic, centralized, unitary system of governance’30 (Preamble) and it accepts the role of the glorious history of historic people’s movements, armed conflict, dedication and sacrifice undertaken by Nepalese people that ensures political participation to ensure economic equality, prosperity and social justice for all people. Sarmila Bagale notes that women’s empowerment is demonstrated by their election-based entry into politics for the purpose of enforcing the constitution and by the ensuing attitude of ‘we can do it’ that permeates contemporary society. It is anticipated that women who were marginalized before the adoption of the constitution 2015 will take a more active part in the growth and prosperity of the nation.31 From this background, we can assume that Nepal has made significant progress on women’s rights and political participation.

The academic research works available mainly in this sector focus on political and socio-economic transformation of Nepalese women. Jeevan Raj Sharma and Antonio Donini (2010) view that there is clear evidence of qualitative changes on the aspects of women’s lives which seem more powerful than the normal process of change. They also believe that the current transition process is bringing about significant changes in important political, economic and sociocultural relationships. While the Maoists have played a major role in this process, other elements also significantly contributed to it.32 Yadav (2016) opines the following remarks on the achievement of present constitution of Nepal as it is also explicitly stated in the 2015 that the women would not face any form of gender-based discrimination. Women now have equal rights over inheritance, protection from gender-based violence and reproductive health under the new constitution.33 The political movement with specific guideline can have some intended results as Nepalese women got from the conflict of Nepal. In fact, the political movement which was followed by a successful peace process, led to structural changes by creating an enabling environment for women to exercise their political power. Women politics in Nepal moved from the hard conditions of civil conflict, women demonstration and transformation. In line with this, the conflict of Nepal had ultimately brought many positives changes especially for women. The representation of women in the first and second constituent assembly was a historic representation.

The present constitution of Nepal has given sufficient space to women in political and decision-making level and in the future, it will increase their capacity to fight for equality and justice. Again, it will by design reduce women’s socio-economic and cultural vulnerability from Nepalese society. The access of Nepalese women in political field through electoral process can increase their representation in practice. The many women in numbers can participate in political level; it becomes easier to implement the constitution of Nepal. The positive attitude of women and their voice ‘yes we can do’ attitude has grown among the women is a good sign for women’s political movement and it will enhance the prosperity and equality in politico-economic sector as well. The wave of a political conflict and the mass political movement heralded in the drafting of a new Constitution that ended a decade long political violent of Nepal. Offering the right to gender equality as a fundamental principle is one obvious tendency in this process of constitutional amendment. Realizing gender equality and allowing women to participate in politics is a standard of contemporary political values that protects each citizen’s human rights. In the twenty-first century, widely accepted view is the inclusion of rights of women in which the women can enjoy democratic legitimacy and they feel they are the product of some process of public participation that reflects the composition of the population.

The 2017 local election was significant for women’s political representation in Nepal. At least 40.4 per cent had to be nominated by the political parties in 753 local units. Of these 35,041 elected representatives, 40.96 per cent women got victory and in the political history of Nepal it was a great achievement.34 In the case of national election held for Federal legislature parliament, in South Asian countries, Nepal tops the index of women in political participation which is the significant result of the political shift of inclusive democracy of Nepal.35 The 2015 Nepalese Constitution recognizes that everyone has the right to live in dignity and guarantees 33 per cent of women equal representation in all political spheres. It also eliminates discrimination based on class, caste, sex, gender and other categories. The constitutional allowance of women to hold positions of political and decision-making authority would undoubtedly lessen the socioeconomic and cultural vulnerabilities that women face in Nepalese society. Women’s participation in politics through election processes to carry out the Constitution and their growing ‘yes we can do’ mentality are predicted to contribute to equality and success in the economy as well.

CONCLUSION

The constitution looks at women’s official political participation, such as their ability to choose political leadership roles, take part in politics and influence the political process after being elected. The advancements in these three areas of political participation of women since 2015 seems positive. It draws attention to national trends and advancements as well as obstacles preventing women from participating in the politics. In doing so, it examines efforts to demonstrate that, while political quotas are prevalent, there is the overwhelming evidence of their successful implementation. The women’s advocacy movement is important because it has the potential to advance gender equality and drive change. When considering practical strategies, it is important to ensure that, once elected, women have a meaningful influence on decision-making and resource allocation.

In addition, political philosophy of every party is the main concern for the participation of women in response to the crisis of the modern republican country Nepal which has subsequently adopted the fundamental principles for the social model in the constitution. In such a case, it provides a philosophical discussion of inclusive democratic system and women can see the practice of political participation in national politics. Then, it creates a congenial environment between the legal and moral obligation of rights and questions the moral justifications offered for the right to inclusive political participation of women. For this, Nepalese Constitution acknowledges that all citizens shall be equal before law and in rights of women (Article 38) and it accepts that every woman shall have equal lineage right without gender-based discrimination and they have right to participate in all bodies of the State based on the principle of proportional inclusion.36 If we observe the bright picture of women that the post-conflict constitution mirrors it seem positive and still there are some challenges in this sector. Due to educational background and political experiences compared to their male counterparts, women have inadequate political power to enjoy equal rights. For this, even at present the political role of all political parties seem to use the Constitutional rights to transform the socio-economic life of the women of Nepal. The status of women and their position in politics highlights some of the social and cultural issues with the country moving toward more women-friendly approaches. The study reflects the progress of women’s status and their increasing political participation that can bring changes in modern society.

NOTES

1. National Population and Housing Census 2021.

2. The Constitution of Nepal, Articles 38 and 38(5).

3. Interim Constitution, Nepal.

4. WHR, A Journal Towards Empowerment and Status of Single Women in Nepal, 7.

5. Stump, The Geography of Religion: Faith, Place and Space.

6. Adams and Sydie, Sociological Theory, 276.

7. Sachedina, ‘Globalization, Religion and Women’, 11.

8. Yogmaya is also credited with founding the Nari Samiti, the first Nepali women’s organization, in 1918. This group was the driving force for Nepal’s 1920 decision to abolish the Sati Pratha (Aziz, 1993).

9. Foucault, ‘The Order of Discourse’, 210.

10. Bem, In the Lenses of Gender: Transforming the Debate on Sexual Inequality.

11. Yadav, Social Transformation in Post-Conflict Nepal: A Gender Perspective, 30.

12. Bourdieu, Masculine Domination, 99.

13. Ibid.

14. Eyben, ‘Supporting Inclusive and Democratic Ownership. A “How to Note” for Donors’.

15. MacKinnon, Toward a Feminist Theory of the State.

16. Thapa and Sijapati, 2006, 15.

17. Partyless political system introduced by King Mahendra that lasted for 30 years.

18. Yadav, Social Transformation in Post-Conflict Nepal: A Gender Perspective, 2016, 37.

19. Slavu, ‘The 2008 Constituent Assembly Election: Social Inclusion for Peace’, 235.

20. Report on Gender Mapping in the Field of Elections, 2.

21. Upreti, ‘Resistance Movement in Conflict Transformation and Social Change’, 2008, 37.

22. Yadav, Social Transformation in Post-Conflict Nepal: A Gender Perspective.

23. The Constitution of the Kingdom of Nepal 1990.

24. Des Chene, ‘Nepali Women’s Movement: Experiences, Critiques, Commentaries’, 294.

25. The forty-point charter, which is included in 19, was submitted to the government of Nepal in 1996 by CPN (Maoist).

26. Tamang, ‘The Politics of Conflict and Difference of Conflict in Politics: The Women’s Movement in Nepal’, 73.

27. Sharma and Prasain, ‘Gender Dimensions of the People’s War: Some Reflections on the Experiences of Rural Women’, 152.

28. Women in National Parliaments— www.ipu.org, 26 April.

29. Bhattarai and Budd (2008). ‘Political Parties in Nepal: Opportunities and Challenges’, 75-88.

30. Preamble of the Constitution of Nepal, 2015.

31. Bagale, ‘Participation of Nepali Women in Politics’.

32. Sharma and Donini, ‘Towards a Great Transformation: The Maoist Insurgency and Local Perceptions of Social Transformation in Nepal’, 20.

33. Yadav, Social Transformation in Post-Conflict Nepal: A Gender Perspective, 52.

34. Nepal’s Locally Elected Women Representatives: Exploratory Study of Needs and Capacity, 6.

35. Shekhawat ‘Women in parliament: Nepal top, Bangladesh 4th in South Asia’. According to data released by Inter-Parliamentary Union, Nepal ranks first, Afghanistan ranks second, Pakistan third, Bangladesh fourth, India fifth, Bhutan sixth, Maldives seventh and Sri Lanka obtains eighth position in SAARC region.

36. Article 38(4) of the Constitution of Nepal, 2015.

REFERENCES

Acharya, Tulasi, ‘Nepal Himalaya: Women, Politics and Administration’, Journal of International Women’s Studies, vol. 18, no. 4, 2017. Retrieved on 5 July 2018 http://vc.bridgew.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1972&context=jiws.

Adams, B.N. and Sydie, R.A. (2009). Sociological Theory. New Delhi: Vanisagar Publication.

Aziz, Barbara Nimri (1993). Shakti Yogmaya: A Tradition of Dissent in Nepal. Kathmandu: Tribhuvan University.

Bagale, Sarmila. ‘Participation of Nepali Women in Politics’, The Rising Nepal, vol. LIII, no. 228, 2018. Retrieved on 5 June 2018 http://therisingnepal.org.np/news/24422.

Bem, S. (1994). In the Lenses of Gender: Transforming the Debate on Sexual Inequality. New Haven: Yale University Press.

Bennett, Lyn. (1983). Dangerous Wives and Sacred Sisters. New York: Columbia University Press.

Bhattarai, K. and Budd, D. (2008). Political Parties in Nepal: Opportunities and Challenges. The Journal of the Institute of Justice & International Studies, 8: 75-88.

Bourdieu, P. (2001). Masculine Domination. Cambridge: Cambridge Polity Press.

Des Chene, M. (1997) ‘Nepali Women’s Movement: Experiences, Critiques, Commentaries’, Studies in Nepali History and Society, vol. 2, no. 2: 291-7.

Dhungana, Raj Kumar. ‘Nepali Hindu Women’s Thorny Path to Liberation’, Journal of Education and Research, vol. 4, no. 1. 2014, Retrieved on 11 July 2018. http://oaji.net/articles/2017/6030-1519944455.pdf

Douglas, Mary (1970). Natural Symbols: Explorations in Cosmology. New York: Vintage.

Eyben, Rosalind (2010). ‘Supporting Inclusive and Democratic Ownership. A “How to Note” for Donors. Institute of Development Studies.

Foucault, M. (1981). ‘The Order of Discourse’, R. Young (ed.), Untying The Text: A Post-Structuralist Reader. Boston: Routledge & Kegan Paul.

International Crisis Group (ICG) (2003). Nepal Backgrounder: Ceasefire-Soft Landing or Strategic Pause? Kathmandu/Brussels: ICG.

Jha, Bina (2015). ‘Women in politics: Equal treatment is a must’. The Himalayan Times. https://thehimalayantimes.com/opinion/women-in-politics-equal-treatment-is-a-must/.

Lal, Abha. ‘Revisiting revisionist history’, My Republica. Retrieved on 16 July 2018. https://myrepublica.nagariknetwork.com/news/revisiting-revisionist-history/.

MacKinnon, Catharine. (1989). Toward a Feminist Theory of the State, Harvard University Press.

Marit, Haug and Aadne Aasland (2015). ‘Exploring Dimensions of Women’s Social Exclusion and Inclusion in Nepal’. Retrieved on 12 June 2018 https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/08039410.2015.1114517?journalCode=sfds20.

National Population and Housing Census 2021 (National Report).

Pradhan, Pratibha. ‘The Status of Women in Political Participation in Nepal’, The Himalayan Review. Retrieved on 10 July 2018. https://www.nepjol.info/index.php/HR/article/view/2415/2155

Risal, Susan. ‘Conflict-hit women: Still far from justice’, The Himalayan. Retrieved on 11 July 2018. https://thehimalayantimes.com/opinion/conflict-hit-women-still-far-from-justice/

Sachedina, A. (2003). ‘Globalization, Religion and Women’. Critical Half, 1(1), 11-14.

Sharma, Jeevan Raj and Antonio Donini (2010). ‘Towards a Great Transformation: The Maoist Insurgency and Local Perceptions of Social Transformation in Nepal’, Feinstein International Center. Retrieved on 12 July 2018 http://fic.tufts.edu/assets/great-transformation.pdf.

Sharma, M. and Prasain, D. (2004). Gender Dimensions of the People’s War: Some Reflections on the Experiences of Rural Women. Himalayan ‘People’s War’: Nepal’s Maoist Rebellion. Michael Hutt, ed., London: Hurst and Company, 152-65.

Slavu, Catinca (2012). ‘The 2008 Constituent Assembly Election: Social Inclusion for Peace’, Nepal in Transition: From People’s War to Fragile Peace. Eds. Sebastian Von Einsiedel, David M. Malone & Suman Pradhan. New Delhi: Cambridge University Press.

Stiglitz, J. (1998). Towards a new Paradigm for Development: Strategies, Policies and Process. Retrieved on 1 August 2018. http://web.worldbank.org/archive/website01013/WEB/IMAGES/PREBISCH.PDF.

Stump, R. (2008). The Geography of Religion: Faith, Place and Space. Maryland: Rowman and Littlefield Publishers.

Tamang, Sierra (2009). The Politics of Conflict and Difference of Conflict in Politics: The Women’s Movement in Nepal. Feminist Review, 91, 61-80.

Thapa, Deepak and Bandita Sijapati (2006). A Kingdom Under Siege: Nepal’s Maoist Insurgency, 1996 to 2004. London/New York: Zed Books.

The Constitution of the Kingdom of Nepal, 1990, Kathmandu: Law Books Management Board.

The Interim Constitution of Nepal, 2007, Kathmandu: Law Books Management Board.

The Constitution of Nepal, 2015, The Government of Nepal: Law Books Management Board.

Upreti, B.R. (2008). ‘Resistance Movement in Conflict Transformation and Social Change’. Kathmandu: Human and Natural Resource Center.

Whelpton, J. (2005). A History of Nepal. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.

WHR (2010). A Journal Towards Empowerment and Status of Single Women in Nepal. Kathmandu.

Yadav, P. (2016). Social Transformation in Post-Conflict Nepal: A Gender Perspective. London: Routledge.

Yami, H. (2007). People’s War and Women’s Liberation in Nepal. Kathmandu: Janadhwani Publication.

Contributors

BHIM NATH REGMI Associate Professor, Tribhuvan University, Nepal.

NARAYANI DEVKOTA is a lecturer in sociology at Saraswati Multiple Campus, affiliated with Tribhuvan University and regularly contributes articles on contemporary issues to Kantipur National Daily.

PURNA BAHADUR KARKI Ph.D. is a Postdoctoral research fellow at the Institute of Global Studies, Tokyo University of Foreign Studies. Currently, he is engaged in research on Post-Conflict Reconciliations and Challenges in Nepal.

PRABHAT CHHETRI holds an LL.M. in Constitutional Law and International Law from Tribhuvan University. She serves as Assistant Government Attorney at the Office of the Attorney General in Nepal.

REWATI RAJ TRIPATHI Ph.D. Scholar at the Law Campus ofTribhuvan University Exhibition Road, Kathmandu, Nepal. He has previously held a Joint Secretary within the Government of Nepal.

SARMILA BAGALE, Tribhuvan University, Nepal.

SARITA NANDMEHAR, Ph.D. scholar at the Centre for South Asian Studies in Jawaharlal Nehru University (JNU), New Delhi, India.

SHOVA PATHAK is Under Secretary, Government of Nepal. M.A. English (Tribhuvan University), LL.M. Criminal Justice (Purbanchal University).

SHIVA PRASAD PAUDEL (Dr). has earned a Ph.D. in law and a teaching faculty at Kathmandu University School of Law.

SUJIT KUMAR DATTA Professor, at the Department of International Relations, Chittagong University, Chittagong, Bangladesh. He was a doctoral fellow at the School of Political Science and Public Administration, Shandong University, China.

TUMPA PAUL is a doctoral fellow at the School of Political Science and Public Administration, Shandong University, China.